<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Nikola's space on the web</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.nikolasander.com/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.nikolasander.com" />
<updated>2014-10-26T00:26:17+01:00</updated>
<id>http://www.nikolasander.com/</id>
<author>
  <name>Nikola Sander</name>
  <uri>http://www.nikolasander.com/</uri>
  <email>nikola.sander@oeaw.ac.at</email>
</author>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Big Open Data Reveal About the Cultural Evolution]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.nikolasander.com/culture-viz/" />
  <id>http://www.nikolasander.com/cultural-history</id>
  <published>2014-08-05T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2014-08-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Nikola Sander</name>
    <uri>http://www.nikolasander.com</uri>
    <email>nikola.sander@oeaw.ac.at</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;What is the best way to visualise large and complex networks with directional connections? Traditional flow maps that show flows as lines drawn atop of a world map are usually a tough sell. Animated network visualisations work well for &lt;a href=&quot;www.wired.com/2014/03/plane-viz/&quot;&gt;airline traffic&lt;/a&gt;, but it’s not so easy to show differences in the sizes of migration flows without overcrowding the graphic. Inspired by software originally developed for genome data, I have been developing circular migration plots together with my colleagues in Vienna. But I don’t think this is the best possible way to visualise (migration) flow data. So, I always keep my eyes open for new inspiration and ideas. 
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Last week, I received a call from Kara Manke, who was writing on a great &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.npr.org/blogs/goatsandsoda/2014/08/01/336646562/how-cultures-move-across-continents&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;story&lt;/a&gt; for National Public Radio and wanted to hear my comments on a new study of cultural evolution. Thanks Kara, for introducing me to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencemag.org/content/345/6196/558.short&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;study by Maximilian Schich and colleagues&lt;/a&gt;! The authors use network modelling to examine the movement of artists around Europe and the Americas over the past 2000 years. 
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Once the paper was published in &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; on August 1, I was delighted to see the authors made their data freely available in the supplementary materials. The Freebase dataset revealed a breadth of information on the year and place of individual people’s birth and death on a level of detail that wasn’t immediately obvious to me from reading the paper. I realised that their data could actually be re-arranged into the matrix format that I work with when analysing migration flow data. I became extremely curious as to what a circular plot (that we had been using to show &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.global-migration.info/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;global migration flows&lt;/a&gt;) would reveal about the cultural evolution. I wanted to explore the pros and cons of each visualisation approach by comparing them directly for the same underlying dataset. #opendata&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
But the circular plot is suited for showing flows at the region or country level, and not for geo-coded data. So, I decided to select the cities that recoded a large number of births and deaths of notable people (i.e. at least 170 over the two centuries). I then identified the country (2012 geography) of each location (Freebase give the latitude &amp;amp; longitude) with the open-source GIS software QGIS. I omitted all persons who died in the same place as they were born, and grouped all remaining ‘migrants’ into 7 time periods based on the year of death. I calculated the number of birth-to-death migrants between the selected 88 cities for each time period and nested the cities within countries.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The visualisation let’s you directly compare the sizes of flows across space and time. Places of birth and death are represented by the circle’s segments and each country/place is assigned a unique colour. Flows have the same colour as the place of birth, and the width indicates their size. There is also gap between flow and place of death. 
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Please stop by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com/cultural-evolution&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; that features the visualisation and provides some more details!	
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com/cultural-evolution/embed.html&quot; width=&quot;620px&quot; height=&quot;700px&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com/culture-viz/&quot;&gt;What Big Open Data Reveal About the Cultural Evolution&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nikola Sander at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com&quot;&gt;Nikola's space on the web&lt;/a&gt; on August 05, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Visualising internal migration in Germany]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.nikolasander.com/migration-flows-in-germany/" />
  <id>http://www.nikolasander.com/migration-in-germany</id>
  <published>2014-06-15T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2014-06-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Nikola Sander</name>
    <uri>http://www.nikolasander.com</uri>
    <email>nikola.sander@oeaw.ac.at</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I developed an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.german-migration.info&quot;&gt;interactive visualisation&lt;/a&gt; of internal migration in Germany together with &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/metropop_eu&quot;&gt;Ramon Bauer&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://null2.net&quot;&gt;Johannes Schmidt&lt;/a&gt;. The newspaper &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.welt.de&quot;&gt;DIE WELT&lt;/a&gt; published a nice story about the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.welt.de/wirtschaft/article129117096/Junge-Menschen-ziehen-massenhaft-in-die-Metropolen.html&quot;&gt;“renaissance of the metropolitan areas”&lt;/a&gt; on June 17. I also got a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.comparativepopulationstudies.de/index.php/CPoS/article/view/89/174&quot;&gt;journal article&lt;/a&gt; published that introduces a new dataset and discusses the key trends since 1995.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/images/german_internal.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/german_internal.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-read-the-circular-migration-plot&quot;&gt;How to read the circular migration plot&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Origins and destinations are represented by the circle’s segments. Each region/county is assigned a colour. Flows have the same colour as their origin and the width indicates their size. The direction of the flow is also shown by the white space between flow and destination. Only directional flows with at least 1,000 migrants are shown, and only flows between counties that had movements (inflows + outflows) of more than 12,000 people in 2010 are included.&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com/migration-flows-in-germany/&quot;&gt;Visualising internal migration in Germany&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nikola Sander at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com&quot;&gt;Nikola's space on the web&lt;/a&gt; on June 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Treat immigrants as you would want others to treat your fellow nationals living abroad]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.nikolasander.com/goldenrule/" />
  <id>http://www.nikolasander.com/goldenrule</id>
  <published>2014-05-18T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2014-05-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Nikola Sander</name>
    <uri>http://www.nikolasander.com</uri>
    <email>nikola.sander@oeaw.ac.at</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a title=&quot;European Parliament&quot; href=&quot;http://www.europarl.europa.eu/portal/en&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;European Parliamentary elections&lt;/a&gt; are around the corner. International migration is an important but very complex topic. It’s not easy to get a glimpse of which countries people are moving from and to, and how trends change over time (new insights &lt;a title=&quot;Science&quot; href=&quot;http://www.sciencemag.org/content/343/6178/1520&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). The complexity of migration flows paired with a lack of adequate data and insightful research reports resulted in migration becoming a politically-contentious topic.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
It’s &lt;a title=&quot;OECD&quot; href=&quot;http://www.oecd.org/els/mig/imo2013.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;no secret&lt;/a&gt; that migration flows to Western and Southern Europe increased substantially in the last decade. The size of immigrant populations (measured by the &lt;a title=&quot;United Nations stock data&quot; href=&quot;http://esa.un.org/unmigration/TIMSO2013/migrantstocks2013.htm?msdo&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;United Nations&lt;/a&gt; as those who were born in another country) grew hand-in-hand with concerns about jobs, public welfare, crime et cetera.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
But looking at immigrant populations tells only one side of the migration story!
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a title=&quot;United Nations stock data&quot; href=&quot;http://esa.un.org/unmigration/TIMSO2013/migrantstocks2013.htm?msdo&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;United Nations data&lt;/a&gt; show that many European countries have sizeable populations of nationals living abroad, and in many cases the numbers increased between 1990 and 2010. Take a look at Belgium, Denmark, Finland, Netherlands and the UK in the chart below!
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Let’s take one step forward by treating immigrants coming to your country as you would want other countries to treat your fellow nationals (or yourself!) living abroad!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;http://cf.datawrapper.de/0gWjq/3/&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;allowfullscreen&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;webkitallowfullscreen&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;mozallowfullscreen&quot; oallowfullscreen=&quot;oallowfullscreen&quot; msallowfullscreen=&quot;msallowfullscreen&quot; width=&quot;550&quot; height=&quot;420&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com/goldenrule/&quot;&gt;Treat immigrants as you would want others to treat your fellow nationals living abroad&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nikola Sander at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com&quot;&gt;Nikola's space on the web&lt;/a&gt; on May 18, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Video Introducing our research on The Global Flow of People]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.nikolasander.com/video-intro/" />
  <id>http://www.nikolasander.com/video-intro</id>
  <published>2014-04-15T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2014-04-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Nikola Sander</name>
    <uri>http://www.nikolasander.com</uri>
    <email>nikola.sander@oeaw.ac.at</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A very pleasant way to avoid death by PowerPoint in conference presentations is to use visuals! Whiteboard animations allow you to visualise almost any complex method or finding in a way that is easily understandable by your audience (more details on the power of visuals &lt;a title=&quot;Huffingtonpost&quot; href=&quot;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/phil-simon/the-persuasive-power-of-v_b_5093192.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a title=&quot;HBR&quot; href=&quot;http://blogs.hbr.org/2014/04/what-i-learned-watching-150-hours-of-ted-talks/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). An animated presentation video is definitely an effective combination of verbal and visual information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This 4 minute video introduces our research on quantifying global international migration flows, which was published in &lt;a title=&quot;Science&quot; href=&quot;http://www.sciencemag.org/content/343/6178/1520&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Science &lt;/a&gt;on March 28, 2014 (free access &lt;a title=&quot;The Global Flow of People&quot; href=&quot;http://www.global-migration.info&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). I produced the video using &lt;a title=&quot;GoAnimate&quot; href=&quot;http://goanimate.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GoAnimate &lt;/a&gt;within 2 days. Making such animated whiteboard videos doesn’t require any magic, just some good ideas on how to visualise complex content, and a great online tool such as GoAnimate. (please turn on your speakers)
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/IomLx1DNvx4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com/video-intro/&quot;&gt;Video Introducing our research on The Global Flow of People&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nikola Sander at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com&quot;&gt;Nikola's space on the web&lt;/a&gt; on April 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Global Flow of People at Your Fingertips]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.nikolasander.com/fingertips/" />
  <id>http://www.nikolasander.com/fingertips</id>
  <published>2014-04-15T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2014-04-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Nikola Sander</name>
    <uri>http://www.nikolasander.com</uri>
    <email>nikola.sander@oeaw.ac.at</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Our new interactive data visualisation available at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.global-migration.info&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;global-migration.info&lt;/a&gt; offers you unique information on international migration flows at your fingertips. Coded by &lt;a href=&quot;http://null2.net/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Null2&lt;/a&gt; using &lt;a href=&quot;http://d3js.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;d3.js&lt;/a&gt;, our tool called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.global-migration.info&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Global Flow of People&lt;/a&gt; allows the public, policy-makers, and scientists to explore for themselves where everyone was migrating in the world between 1990 and 2010. Give it a try! Hover your mouse over the graphic below, click on a coloured segment of the circle, and start exploring!
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The Global Flow of People is a group effort by me, Guy Abel, Ramon Bauer, Johannes Schmidt, Andi Pieper and Elvira Stein.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The data shown in this visualisation is available in the supplementary materials of our paper published in &lt;a title=&quot;Science&quot; href=&quot;http://www.sciencemag.org/content/343/6178/1520&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which can be accessed via &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.global-migration.info&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;global-migration.info&lt;/a&gt; with no paywall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://global-migration-info.s3.amazonaws.com/embed.html&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; height=&quot;680px&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com/fingertips/&quot;&gt;The Global Flow of People at Your Fingertips&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nikola Sander at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com&quot;&gt;Nikola's space on the web&lt;/a&gt; on April 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Circular Migration Plot Gallery]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.nikolasander.com/gallery" />
  <id>http://www.nikolasander.com/gallery</id>
  <published>2014-04-05T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2014-04-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Nikola Sander</name>
    <uri>http://www.nikolasander.com</uri>
    <email>nikola.sander@oeaw.ac.at</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here you find a selection of circular migration plots that I’ve created in 2013/14. Frustrated with the lack of progress in the area of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gislounge.com/overview-flow-mapping/&quot;&gt;geography/GIS&lt;/a&gt; to visualise flow data, I decided to look outside the discipline and, luckily, came across Martin Krzywinski’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://circos.ca&quot;&gt;Circos&lt;/a&gt;. I ditched the map and decided to go circular.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
If you’d like to use an image from this gallery, please
* keep the caption information,
* don’t call it an infographic (because it is a data visualisation),
* respect the cc license guidelines by citing the source: Nikola Sander, Guy Abel and Ramon Bauer, Wittgenstein Centre/Vienna Institute of Demography.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Simple circular plot of migration flows within and between world regions in 2005-10.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/circular_icon.png&quot; alt=&quot;Circular plot&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Simple circular plot of migration flows within and between world regions in 2005-10. Only flows with at least 70,000 migrants are shown.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Circular plot of migration flows within and between world regions in 2005-10. Only flows with at least 70,000 migrants are shown. 
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/circular-plot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Circular plot&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Circular plot of migration flows within and between world regions in 2005-10. Only flows with at least 70,000 migrants are shown. The outer stacked bars provide additional information on the number of immigrants by origin region (inner bar), and emigrants by destination (outer bar). For receiving countries with a net migration gain, the inner bar is higher/longer than the outer bar.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Circular plot of migration flows between 50 countries in 2005-10.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/circular_top50.png&quot; alt=&quot;Circular plot&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Circular plot of migration flows between 50 countries in 2005-10. Only flows with at least 60,000 migrants are shown.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com/gallery&quot;&gt;Circular Migration Plot Gallery&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nikola Sander at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com&quot;&gt;Nikola's space on the web&lt;/a&gt; on April 05, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Global Migration Flows in One Gorgeous Chart]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.nikolasander.com/one-gorgeous-chart" />
  <id>http://www.nikolasander.com/one-gorgeous-chart</id>
  <published>2014-03-31T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2014-03-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Nikola Sander</name>
    <uri>http://www.nikolasander.com</uri>
    <email>nikola.sander@oeaw.ac.at</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Social scientists don’t get accepted into the holy halls of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencemag.org/&quot;&gt;Science&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com&quot;&gt;Nature&lt;/a&gt; too often. It requires novel and broadly important findings on a topic that is of interest to the scientific community and the general public.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Perhaps the most difficult thing about getting published is to catch the editor’s attention in the blink of an eye. Title &amp;amp; abstract are crucial elements of a paper, and if a crisp-clear title &amp;amp; abstract grabbed enough of the editors attention to get him/her to quickly scan the paper, great visuals are more likely than endless jargon to persuade him/her to actually read the whole thing.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Effective data visualisations in scientific papers not only help to get through the review process, they are also key to getting attention by the media and, subsequently, the general public. With journalists or Twitter users, you might only have &lt;em&gt;half&lt;/em&gt; a blink of an eye to catch their attention.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
That sounds almost impossible to accomplish with social science research, doesn’t it? Well, no! But my experience tells me that it requires some effort and out-of-the-box thinking.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
My colleague &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oeaw.ac.at/vid/staff/staff_guy_abel.shtml‎&quot;&gt;Guy Abel&lt;/a&gt; and I published a paper on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencemag.org/content/343/6178/1520&quot;&gt;Quantifying Global International Migration Flows&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;em&gt;Science * on March 28 (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.global-migration.info&quot;&gt;go here for free access&lt;/a&gt;. But the journey didn’t end there. Our work has been picked up by the international media and spread further via Twitter, which gave our research a much wider coverage than we could have ever imagined.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
It became pretty clear pretty quickly that &lt;strong&gt;one gorgeous chart&lt;/strong&gt; of migration between 50 countries (shown below) was playing a key role in spreading the word. First featured in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://qz.com/192440&quot;&gt;story by Nick Stockton&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/StocktonSays‎&quot;&gt;@StocktonSays&lt;/a&gt;) in &lt;a href=&quot;http://qz.com/&quot;&gt;Quartz&lt;/a&gt; (The Atlantic), the chart appeared on more than 50 websites/blogs and several thousand Tweets in the week following publication.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The one gorgeous chart is part of a whole &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.net/dataviz/gallery&quot;&gt;gallery&lt;/a&gt; of circular migration plots that I’ve created. About 1.5 years ago, I was so frustrated with the lack of progress in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gislounge.com/overview-flow-mapping/&quot;&gt;geography/GIS&lt;/a&gt; to visualise flow data, that I decided to look outside the discipline. Martin Krzywinski’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://circos.ca&quot;&gt;Circos&lt;/a&gt; inspired me to ditch the map (a hard thing to do for geographers!) and *go circular&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
After a year and a bit of tweaking the configuration files in Circos and playing with different input data formats (see here for details on how to do plots yourself), I had created a visualisation technique that let Guy’s new migration flow estimates shine in a way that brings out their best: global coverage and comparability.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
So, the equation is simple: &lt;em&gt;important topic + unique new data of global coverage + effective, eye-catching visualisation + surprising findings + a fantastic team + a bit of luck = publication in top-tier journal + successful science communication.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/images/circular_top50.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/circular_top50.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;Circular migration plot of flows between 50 countries in 2005-10. Image by Nikola Sander, Wittgenstein Centre, Vienna. More details: www.global-migration.info&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’d like to use this image, please keep the caption information and respect the cc license guidelines by citing the source: Nikola Sander, Guy Abel and Ramon Bauer, Wittgenstein Centre for Demography and Global Human Capital, Vienna.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com/one-gorgeous-chart&quot;&gt;Global Migration Flows in One Gorgeous Chart&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nikola Sander at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com&quot;&gt;Nikola's space on the web&lt;/a&gt; on March 31, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Our Research in the Media]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.nikolasander.com/in-the-media" />
  <id>http://www.nikolasander.com/in-the-press</id>
  <published>2014-03-31T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2014-03-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Nikola Sander</name>
    <uri>http://www.nikolasander.com</uri>
    <email>nikola.sander@oeaw.ac.at</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The level of media attention our research on The Global Flow of People has received since Guy Abel and I published our paper &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencemag.org/content/343/6178/1520&quot;&gt;Quantifying Global International Migration Flows&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; on March 28 is absolutely mind blowing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like most success stories, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.global-migration.info&quot;&gt;The Global Flow of People&lt;/a&gt; has been a fantastic group effort by me, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.metropop.eu/&quot;&gt;Ramon Bauer&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oeaw.ac.at/vid/staff/staff_guy_abel.shtml‎&quot;&gt;Guy Abel&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://null2.net/&quot;&gt;Null2&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.elvirastein.com/&quot;&gt;Elvira Stein&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks also to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oeaw.ac.at/wic&quot;&gt;Wittgenstein Centre for Demography and Global Human Capital&lt;/a&gt; and the   &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oeaw.ac.at/vid&quot;&gt;Vienna Institute of Demography&lt;/a&gt; for their support.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here’s a selection of all the stories and blog posts that have popped up across the globe.&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://qz.com/192440/where-everyone-in-the-world-is-migrating-in-one-gorgeous-chart/&quot;&gt;Where everyone in the world is migrating—in one gorgeous chart; Quartz, by Nick Stockton, published March 27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.scientificamerican.com/observations/2014/03/28/global-migrant-flows-an-interactive-map/#respond&quot;&gt;Global Migrant Flows: An Interactive Map – Scientific American, by Geoffrey Giller, published March 28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.newscientist.com/article/dn25311-rising-tide-of-migration-is-a-myth-say-global-stats.html&quot;&gt;Rising tide of migration is a myth, say global stats; New Scientist, by Jon White, published March 27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://phys.org/news/2014-03-duo-quantify-global-human-migration.html&quot;&gt;Research duo quantify global human migration numbers; Phys.org, by Bob Yirka, published March 28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fastcoexist.com/3028211/visualized/visualizing-which-countries-people-are-trying-to-get-away-from-and-where-theyre-g&quot;&gt;Visualizing Which Countries People Are Trying To Get Away From, And Where They’re Going; Fast Company Co.Exist, by Jessica Leber, published March 27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2014/03/20-years-of-global-migration-in-one-chart/359793/&quot;&gt;20 Years of Global Migration—in One Chart; The Atlantic, by Nick Stockton, published March 28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.internazionale.it/news/societa/2014/03/31/da-dove-vengono-e&quot;&gt;Da dove vengono e dove vanno i migranti; Internationale, March 31&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.spiegel.de/wissenschaft/mensch/datenlese-migration-die-welt-ist-konstant-in-bewegung-a-960820.html&quot;&gt;Die Welt ist konstant in Bewegung; Spiegel Online, March 28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://science.orf.at/stories/1735696/&quot;&gt;Globale Migration seit 1990 stabil; Science ORF, March 28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://derstandard.at/1395363369978/Neue-Studie-Globale-Migration-seit-1990-nahezu-unveraendert&quot;&gt;Neue Studie: Globale Migration seit 1990 nahezu unverändert; Der Standard, March 27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wissenschaft.de/home/-/journal_content/56/12054/3265251/Auf-der-Spur-der-Migranten/&quot;&gt;Auf der Spur der Migranten; Bild der Wissenschart, March 28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.storia.rai.it/gallery-refresh-img/4/default.aspx&quot;&gt;Tutte le migrazioni degli ultimi 20 anni; Rai, March 31&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com/in-the-media&quot;&gt;Our Research in the Media&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nikola Sander at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com&quot;&gt;Nikola's space on the web&lt;/a&gt; on March 31, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Estimating the Lone Spaniard]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.nikolasander.com/lone-spaniard" />
  <id>http://www.nikolasander.com/lone-spaniard</id>
  <published>2014-03-29T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2014-03-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Nikola Sander</name>
    <uri>http://www.nikolasander.com</uri>
    <email>nikola.sander@oeaw.ac.at</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In a paper published in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencemag.org/content/343/6178/1520&quot;&gt;Science&lt;/a&gt; on March 28, Guy Abel and I present a new methodology for estimating bilateral migration flows between 196 countries from United Nations &lt;a href=&quot;http://esa.un.org/unmigration/TIMSO2013/migrantstocks2013.htm&quot;&gt;migrant stock data&lt;/a&gt;. We are absolutely flabbergasted by all the (social) media attention and positive feedback we are getting! When exploring our interactive visualisation of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.global-migration.info&quot;&gt;The Global Flow of People&lt;/a&gt;, you might come across a number that makes you think &lt;em&gt;Huh? That can’t be right!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/images/lone-spaniard.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/lone-spaniard.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Lone Spaniard&lt;/em&gt;, first uncovered by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Null2Berlin&quot;&gt;Leo @ Null2 Berlin&lt;/a&gt;, is likely to cause such a reaction. Why on earth would we estimate the total outflow from Spain to be just 1 in the period 2000 to 2005? We all know from looking at existing flow data published by the UN and Eurostat, that people are constantly migrating! The reasons why we estimate such a small number lie in the way we define migration and in the UN migrant stock data that our estimates are based upon.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
We define migration as the number of people who changed their country of residence over 5-year periods. In contrast, existing flow data define migration as the number of moves that people make in a year. The figure above illustrates how our estimates only capture &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; move per person over 5 years, while all other moves people make; and that are captured by existing flow statistics are just shadows in our estimates. Our data are not per se less accurate, our methodology of linking stocks to flows just requires a different definition of migration. The big advantage of our data is, of course, that we can directly compare the sizes of flows across 196 countries, something that hasn’t been possible so far.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Besides capturing only one move over 5 years, our model also estimated the Lone Spaniard because the stock data for Spain changed in very unusual ways between 2000 and 2005. Normally, we estimate an outflow from a given country because the stocks tell us that the number of people living overseas increased. In addition, our model estimates an outflow of people returning home if the number of foreigners in the country decreases. The Lone Spaniard was caused by no increase in the Spanish population living overseas, and no decrease in the number of foreigners living in Spain. Instead, we saw a strong increase in foreigners, causing a massive immigration wave (which, of course, melt into thin air in the last few years because of the economic crisis).
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The Lone Spaniard really illustrates how our estimates are different from existing flow data. Our focus has not been on estimating the &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; flow for every country in the world. Instead, we present the first ever estimates of migration flows that can be compared across countries and that allow a truly global perspective. Having said that, we are very much aware that this is only a first step, and that both the quality of the underlying stock data and our methodology can be improved.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
If you want to learn more about the (statistical) details of our methodology, please take a look at the supplementary materials of our Science paper (&lt;a href=&quot;/images/Abel_Sander2014.pdf&quot;&gt;Accepted Version&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com/lone-spaniard&quot;&gt;Estimating the Lone Spaniard&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nikola Sander at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com&quot;&gt;Nikola's space on the web&lt;/a&gt; on March 29, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Circular Migration Plots - Do it yourself!]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.nikolasander.com/diy" />
  <id>http://www.nikolasander.com/diy</id>
  <published>2014-03-26T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2014-03-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Nikola Sander</name>
    <uri>http://www.nikolasander.com</uri>
    <email>nikola.sander@oeaw.ac.at</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;You might have seen our colourful circular graphics of global migration flows and wondered, how the heck did they do that? Here is a summary of how to Do It Yourself with your own data!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/images/circular_top50.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/circular_top50.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our VID &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.global-migration.info/VID%20WP%20Visualising%20Migration%20Flow%20Data%20with%20Circular%20Plots.pdf&quot;&gt;working paper&lt;/a&gt; provides the full details. You’ll also need the paper’s supplementary materials to replicate our plots, or to plot your own data.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
We provide instructions on how to create circular migration plots with 3 alternative software packages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://circos.ca&quot;&gt;Circos&lt;/a&gt;: the original; allows for deep customization; my favorite; requires Perl, but no big programming skills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.r-project.org&quot;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt;: for statisticians &amp;amp; data miners; less customization but quick to set up; Guy’s favourite; requires some R skills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.d3js.org/&quot;&gt;d3.js&lt;/a&gt;: Let’s go interactive; customization &amp;amp; interaction; everyone’s favourite; requires sound programming skills; not ideal for printed media&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To create circular plots using Circos, you need to install Perl and several Perl modules, dowload Circos and install Cygwin to run it all on Windows.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Once you’ve set everything up, you can create a plot with Circos’ default settings. Be warned: it doesn’t look very pretty. And it probably reminds you of several other visualisations you have seen on the web. People have been using Circos before to show migration, trade or remittances flows, but IMHO with not such great success.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
To create a plot that visualises migration flows in an effective and visually appealing manner, use my customised configuration files for Circos (see supplementary materials of the VID working paper). I provide two sets of configuration files with accompanying input data; one for a region-level plot, and one for a country-level plot. Take a look at the text files, replicate our plots, get an idea of what all the settings actually mean, and use it for your own data. Let’s make it the new standard for visualising flows!
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Johannes Schmidt created a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jo/circular-migration-plot&quot;&gt;custom library&lt;/a&gt; on Github on how to do interactive plots in d3. Guy Abel also has a &lt;a href=&quot;http://gjabel.wordpress.com/2014/03/28/circular-migration-flow-plots-in-r/&quot;&gt;R-Bloggers post&lt;/a&gt; on how to do these plots in R. For more information please visit &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.global-migration.info&quot;&gt;www.global-migration.info&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com/diy&quot;&gt;Circular Migration Plots - Do it yourself!&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nikola Sander at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com&quot;&gt;Nikola's space on the web&lt;/a&gt; on March 26, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[d3.js - the future of data visualisation]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.nikolasander.com/first-d3" />
  <id>http://www.nikolasander.com/first-d3</id>
  <published>2013-10-20T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2013-10-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Nikola Sander</name>
    <uri>http://www.nikolasander.com</uri>
    <email>nikola.sander@oeaw.ac.at</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There’s a new rock star tool for interactive online visualizations that I discovered recently thanks to my colleagues at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.metropop.eu/&quot;&gt;Metropop.eu&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://null2.net/&quot;&gt;Null2&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;http://d3js.org/&quot;&gt;D3.js – Data-Driven Documents&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/images/d3.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/d3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Adobe Flash being a thing of the past, d3.js lets you create really cool custom-made interactive plots that can be shown on all sorts of devices (smartphone, tablet, laptop). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can even create interactive presentation slides that can be shown in any browser using the new JavaScript slides frameworks like &lt;a href=&quot;http://revealjs.com/&quot;&gt;reveal.js&lt;/a&gt;. How exciting is that! No more boring Powerpoints!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning d3 means diving into html5, css and Javascipt all at once. Hence, my learning curve is very steep, but Scott Murray’s excellent book (&lt;a href=&quot;http://chimera.labs.oreilly.com/books/1230000000345/index.html&quot;&gt;online version)&lt;/a&gt; on visualizations with d3 helped me to accomplish my first task: To include Mike Bostock’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/mbostock/4062006&quot;&gt;chord diagram&lt;/a&gt; into my blog. Here it is. Hurray! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sorry folks. Chord diagram is temporarily unavailable - until I have time to include it into my new Jekyll/Markdown blog.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com/first-d3&quot;&gt;d3.js - the future of data visualisation&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nikola Sander at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com&quot;&gt;Nikola's space on the web&lt;/a&gt; on October 20, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Retirement migration in Australia]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.nikolasander.com/retirement-migration" />
  <id>http://www.nikolasander.com/retirement-migration</id>
  <published>2013-10-19T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2013-10-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Nikola Sander</name>
    <uri>http://www.nikolasander.com</uri>
    <email>nikola.sander@oeaw.ac.at</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My PhD thesis contributes to a better understanding of the dynamics of retirement migration and the likely future trajectory of retirement migration as Australia’s baby boomers enter retirement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/images/Retired-grandma.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Retired-grandma.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A suite of state-of-the-art statistical methods were applied to cross-sectional and longitudinal datasets. The results demonstrate that the incidence and timing of retirement migration is closely related to the transition to retirement, and that large cohort size does not have a negative effect on migration. The impact of retirement migration among the boomers on regional population age structures is projected to be strongest in the retirement destinations of south-east Queensland and northern NSW.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Download my thesis from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://espace.library.uq.edu.au/view/UQ:227846&quot;&gt;University of Queensland&lt;/a&gt; or from &lt;a href=&quot;http://figshare.com/articles/Retirement_Migration_of_the_Baby_Boomers_in_Australia_Beach_Bush_or_Busted_/1050179&quot;&gt;Figshare&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com/retirement-migration&quot;&gt;Retirement migration in Australia&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nikola Sander at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com&quot;&gt;Nikola's space on the web&lt;/a&gt; on October 19, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Projecting international migration]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.nikolasander.com/projections" />
  <id>http://www.nikolasander.com/projections</id>
  <published>2013-10-18T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2013-10-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Nikola Sander</name>
    <uri>http://www.nikolasander.com</uri>
    <email>nikola.sander@oeaw.ac.at</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The global flow of people is a critical component of global human capital projections, especially the intensities of country-to-country flows and the characteristics of people with regards to age, sex and education.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Mostly due to the lack of adequate data, assumptions are commonly constrained to net-migration flows where migrants’ education is assumed to be proportional to the population in their country of origin.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Because of strong selection effects, these assumptions are known to introduce inaccuracies when projecting populations by level of educational attainment.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
At the Wittgenstein Centre, we carry out global population projections using directional migration probabilities in a multi-regional cohort-component framework.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
We draw on a unique new set of estimates of global bilateral migration flows for the 5-year period 2005-10 developed by my colleague Guy J. Abel (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.demographic-research.org/volumes/vol28/18/&quot;&gt;find his latest publication here&lt;/a&gt;). We combine these flows with the “Database on Immigrants in OECD and non-OECD Countries (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oecd.org/migration/databaseonimmigrantsinoecdandnon-oecdcountriesdioc-e.htm&quot;&gt;DIOC&lt;/a&gt;)” to estimate education differentials in country-specific immigration and emigration flows.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The results of the Wittgenstein Centre global human capital projections are documented in a major volume under the title “World Population and Human Capital in the 21st Century”, which is scheduled for publication in early 2014 by Oxford University Press.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Our population projections underly the recently published 2013 &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iiasa.ac.at/web/home/about/news/UN-HDR-relies-on-IIASA-projections.en.html&quot;&gt;United Nations Human Development Report&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Details can also be found in the Wittgenstein Centre 5-year report (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oeaw.ac.at/wic/fileadmin/user_upload/infoFiles/WiCReport08-12w200.pdf&quot;&gt;download full report&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com/projections&quot;&gt;Projecting international migration&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nikola Sander at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com&quot;&gt;Nikola's space on the web&lt;/a&gt; on October 18, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Myths about migration]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.nikolasander.com/myths" />
  <id>http://www.nikolasander.com/myths</id>
  <published>2013-10-17T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2013-10-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Nikola Sander</name>
    <uri>http://www.nikolasander.com</uri>
    <email>nikola.sander@oeaw.ac.at</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Myth-busters update, 28 March 1014:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.newscientist.com/article/dn25311-rising-tide-of-migration-is-a-myth-say-global-stats.html#.U0Be_FfJEgj&quot;&gt;Rising tide of migration is a myth, say global stats!&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
It’s fair to say that demographers, sociologists and economists could have done a better job quantifying and projecting international migration. As a result of differences in definitions and measures across countries, there is as yet no solid empirical evidence about the number of people who move across the globe over a given period of time.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
So, people put their spin on things to depict immigrants as a treat to labour markets, identity, culture and well-being. Population growth in Africa is expected to lead to mass migration to Europe, while the positive economic impacts of migration are often downplayed.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Together with my colleagues, I’m trying my best to let the facts speak for themselves. Here are some of the myths about international migration:
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
1) The intensity of global international migration has been rising continuously since the early 1990s. Our flow data suggest that intensities have remained stable.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
2) Immigration to Europe is set to increase as a result of population growth in sub-Saharan Africa. Today, almost all African migrants come from Northern Africa (e.g. Morocco), where population growth is much slower.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
3) Waves of immigration trigger anti-immigrant attitudes in host countries. Countries like France where anti-immigrant rhetoric has been thriving record much lower net gains from immigration than other European countries.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
4) Climate change will result in mass migration to the developed world. Science suggests that most people will move within their own country, and those who can afford to move across continental borders tend to be well educated.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com/myths&quot;&gt;Myths about migration&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nikola Sander at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com&quot;&gt;Nikola's space on the web&lt;/a&gt; on October 17, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[New data and insights on migration in Germany]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.nikolasander.com/migration-germany" />
  <id>http://www.nikolasander.com/migration-germany</id>
  <published>2013-10-16T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2013-10-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Nikola Sander</name>
    <uri>http://www.nikolasander.com</uri>
    <email>nikola.sander@oeaw.ac.at</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of my current research projects involves the study interregional migration flows in Germany and how patterns have changed over the last 15 years. Such time series analyses have long been hindered by the lack of suitable data.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
To overcome this obstacle, I developed the &lt;strong&gt;German Interal Migration (GIM) Database&lt;/strong&gt;. The database holds annual inter-county (german: Kreise) migration flows for a temporally harmonised geography of 397 regions covering the period 1995 to 2010. Using GIS overlay techniques, I minimised errors due to boundary changes and redistribution of ethnic Germans (Spätaussiedler).
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The data provide a more comprehensive picture of the spatial structure of interregional migration in Germany and how it has changed since reunification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cpos_net.png&quot; alt=&quot;Net flows&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more detailed discussion of the database and key results are published in a paper in Comparative Population Studies titled &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.comparativepopulationstudies.de/index.php/CPoS/article/view/89/174&quot;&gt;Internal migration in Germany, 1995-2010: new insights into East-West migration and re-urbanization&lt;/a&gt;. The flow matrices are available in the supplementary materials.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Data specifications:&lt;/em&gt; Counts represent the annual number of migration events across county boundaries. Within-county moves were not reported. The data are disaggregated by 6 age groups and gender. Age refers to the age at the time of the move. Moves of foreign citizens are included. The migration data used to derive these flow matrices were drawn from the German population register and kindly provided by DESTATIS. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com/migration-germany&quot;&gt;New data and insights on migration in Germany&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nikola Sander at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com&quot;&gt;Nikola's space on the web&lt;/a&gt; on October 16, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Who is a migrant? Defining international movements]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.nikolasander.com/migrant-definitions" />
  <id>http://www.nikolasander.com/definitions</id>
  <published>2013-10-14T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2013-10-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Nikola Sander</name>
    <uri>http://www.nikolasander.com</uri>
    <email>nikola.sander@oeaw.ac.at</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My personal migration history highlights the fallacies of official statistics on migration flows. Depending on how you define migration, I’ve moved between 2 and 11 times in the past 10 years; often with all my belongings on my Troopy’s roof rack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/images/Streadbroke_Island.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Streadbroke_Island.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data on migrant stock (i.e. people living outside their country of birth) would suggest that I’ve been a migrant for 9 years and 6 months (out of 10 years).
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Using the UN definition of a migrant that states that a (long-term) migrant is a person who moves to a country other than that of his/her usual residence for a period of at least 12 months, so that the country of destination becomes his/her new country of residence (United Nations 1998), I moved twice: to Brisbane, Australia in 2006 and to Vienna, Austria in 2010.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Counting all international moves, I changed my country of residence 4 times (to Adelaide as an international student in 2003, return move to Tübingen in 2005, to Gold Coast as occupational trainee in 2005, and to Vienna in 2010)
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Counting all changes of address within countries and across borders, I moved 11 times (not counting temporary stays with friends or relatives).
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
When it comes to migration flow data, definition matters! &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com/migrant-definitions&quot;&gt;Who is a migrant? Defining international movements&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nikola Sander at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com&quot;&gt;Nikola's space on the web&lt;/a&gt; on October 14, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bridging the Science-Society Gap]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.nikolasander.com/bridging-gap" />
  <id>http://www.nikolasander.com/bridging-the-gap</id>
  <published>2013-10-13T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2013-10-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Nikola Sander</name>
    <uri>http://www.nikolasander.com</uri>
    <email>nikola.sander@oeaw.ac.at</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Research findings are typically communicated through scientific journals. While top-ranked journals are essential for anvancing careers in the research community, they are not the best outlet for informing policy makers, journalists and the general public.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/bridging_gap.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bridging the gap&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Interactive visualisations that bring research alive have the power to bridge the gap and to make research more accessible and understandable.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The bottom line is that research is not only about &lt;em&gt;doing&lt;/em&gt; it, it’s also about communicating the findings to those who might be most interested. We need to be aware that this is &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; responsibility!
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
See also this &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.livescience.com/14779-bridging-gap-scientists-public.html&quot;&gt;story&lt;/a&gt; by Marlene Cimons from the National Science Foundation. &lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com/bridging-gap&quot;&gt;Bridging the Science-Society Gap&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Nikola Sander at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nikolasander.com&quot;&gt;Nikola's space on the web&lt;/a&gt; on October 13, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>

</feed>
